Do you know how many choices you make
هل تعرف كم اختيارا تقوم به
in a typical day?
في اي يوم؟
in typical week?
في اي اسبوع؟
I recently did a survey
مؤخرا قمت بعمل استطلاع
with over 2,000 Americans,
على حوالي 2000 امريكي
and the average number of choices
وكان متوسط عدد الاختيارات
that the typical American reports making
التي يقوم بها الامريكي العادي
is about 70 in a typical day.
حوالي السبعين في اي يوم
There was also recently a study done with CEOs
وهناك دراسة اجريت على المدراء التنفيذيين
in which they followed CEOs around for a whole week.
حيث تابعوا المدراء التنفيذيين طوال اسبوع كامل
And these scientists simply documented all the various tasks
وقام اولئك العلماء ببساطة بتوثيق المهام المختلفة
that these CEOs engaged in
التي يقوم بها اولئك المدراء
and how much time they spent engaging
وكم من الوقت يمضون
in making decisions related to these tasks.
في اتخاذ قرارات متعلقة بتلك المهمام
And they found that the average CEO
لكنهم وجدو ان متوسط ما يشارك فيه المدير التنفيذي
engaged in about 139 tasks in a week.
هو حوالي 139 مهمة في الاسبوع
Each task was made up of many, many, many sub-choices of course.
وبالطبع كل مهمة مكونة من العديد و العديد من الاختيارات الفرعية
50 percent of their decisions
50 في المئة من قراراتهم
were made in nine minutes or less.
يتم عمله في 9 دقائق او اقل
Only about 12 percent of the decisions
حوالي 12 بالمئة من القرارات فقط
did they make an hour or more of their time.
يقومون بها في ساعة او اكثر
Think about your own choices.
فكر في اختياراتك.
Do you know how many choices
هل تعلم كم اختيارا
make it into your nine minute category
يمكن تصنيفها في قسم التسع دقائق
versus your one hour category?
في مقابل قسم الساعة؟
How well do you think you're doing
باي قدر تعتقد انك تستغرق
at managing those choices?
في ادارة تلك لاختيارات
Today I want to talk
اليوم اريد الحديث
about one of the biggest modern day choosing problems that we have,
عن احد اكبر مشاكل الاختيار في عصرنا الحديث
which is the choice overload problem.
الا وهي مشكلة الحمل الزائد للاختيار
I want to talk about the problem
اريد الحديث عن المشكلة
and some potential solutions.
وبعض الحلول الجوهرية.
Now as I talk about this problem,
الان وبينما اتحدث عن هذه المشكلة
I'm going to have some questions for you
سوف اطرح عليكم بعض الاسئلة
and I'm going to want to know your answers.
وسوف اكون راغبة في معرفة اجاباتكم.
So when I ask you a question,
فحين اسالكم سؤال,
since I'm blind,
بما انني عمياء,
only raise your hand if you want to burn off some calories.
ارفعوا ايديكم فقط في حال رغبتم في حرق بعض السعرات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Otherwise, when I ask you a question,
والا ,عندما اسأل سؤالا,
and if your answer is yes,
وكانت اجابتكم نعم,
I'd like you to clap your hands.
اريد منكم ان تصفقوا
So for my first question for you today:
سؤالي الاول اليوم.
Are you guys ready to hear about the choice overload problem?
هل انتم جاهزين لتسمعوا عن مشكلة الحمل الزائد للاختيار؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
So when I was a graduate student at Stanford University,
عندما كانت طالبة دراسات عليا في جامعة ستارفورد,
I used to go to this very, very upscale grocery store;
اعتدت الذهاب الى محل بقالة راقي جدا جدا
at least at that time it was truly upscale.
على الاقل في ذلك الوقت كان حقا راقي
It was a store called Draeger's.
كان ذلك المحل يسمى دراجرز
Now this store, it was almost like going to an amusement park.
هذا المحل , كان اشبه بالذهاب الى مدينة ملاهي
They had 250 different kinds of mustards and vinegars
لديهم 250 نوع من الماسترد والخل
and over 500 different kinds
واكثر من 500 نوع مختلف
of fruits and vegetables
من الفواكه والخضار
and more than two dozen different kinds of bottled water --
والعشرا ت من انواع زجاجات المياه--
and this was during a time when we actually used to drink tap water.
كان ذلك في وقت كنا معتادين فعلا على شرب زجاجات المياه
I used to love going to this store,
كنت احب الذهاب الى هذا المحل,
but on one occasion I asked myself,
لكن في احدى المناسبات سألت نفسي,
well how come you never buy anything?
كيف يمكن ان لا اشتري اي شيء ابدا؟
Here's their olive oil aisle.
هذا هو ممر زيت الزيتون.
They had over 75 different kinds of olive oil,
لديهم اكثر من 75 نوع مختلف من زيت الزيتون
including those that were in a locked case
بالاضافة الى تلك التي كانت في عبوات مغلقة
that came from thousand-year-old olive trees.
والتي تم جلبها من اشجار زيتون عمرها آلالاف السنين
So I one day decided to pay a visit to the manager,
فقررت يوما ان اقوم بزيارة للمدير,
and I asked the manager,
وسألت المدير
"Is this model of offering people all this choice really working?"
"هل هذا النموذج من عرض كل هذه الخيارات على الناس مُجدي؟"
And he pointed to the busloads of tourists
وأشار الى حافلات السياح
that would show up everyday,
الذين يقدمون كل يوم
with cameras ready usually.
بكاميرات مُعدة للتصوير في العادة
We decided to do a little experiment,
قررنا ان نقوم بتجربة
and we picked jam for our experiment.
واخترنا المربى لهذه التجربة.
Here's their jam aisle.
هذا هو ممر المربى
They had 348 different kinds of jam.
لديهم 348 نوع مختلف من المربى
We set up a little tasting booth
ووضعنا كشك للتذوق
right near the entrance of the store.
قرب مدخل المتجر مباشرة
We there put out six different flavors of jam
ووضعنا هناك ستة نكهات مختلفة من المربى
or 24 different flavors of jam,
او 24 نكهة مختلفة من المربى
and we looked at two things:
وقمنا بمراقبة شيئين
First, in which case
الاول , في اي الحالات
were people more likely to stop, sample some jam?
يقف الناس لتجربة بعض المربى؟
More people stopped when there were 24, about 60 percent,
معظم الناس توقفوا عندما كانت 24 بنسبة 60 في المئة
than when there were six,
وعندما كان هناك 6 أنواع
about 40 percent.
حوالي 40 في المئة
The next thing we looked at
والشيء الاخر الذي تابعناه
is in which case were people more likely
في اي الحالات كان الناس اكثر قابلية
to buy a jar of jam.
لشراء علبة مربى
Now we see the opposite effect.
نلاحظ الان التاثير العكسي
Of the people who stopped when there were 24,
من الاشخاص الذين توقفوا في حالة ال 24
only three percent of them actually bought a jar of jam.
فقط اربعة في المائة منهم اشترى علبة مربى
Of the people who stopped when there were six,
ومن الناس الذين توقفوا في حالة الستة
well now we saw that 30 percent of them
لاحظنا ان 30 في المائة منهم
actually bought a jar of jam.
قامو بالفعل بشراء المربى
Now if you do the math,
الان، اذا قمت بعمليات حسابية
people were at least six times more likely to buy a jar of jam
الناس يقومون بشراء المربى بستة اضعاف
if they encountered six
اذا قابلوا ستة انواع
than if they encountered 24.
اكثر من اذا واجهوا 23 نوعا
Now choosing not to buy a jar of jam
الان اختيار عدم شراء المربى
is probably good for us --
ربما كان جيد بالنسبة لنا--
at least it's good for our waistlines --
على الاقل جيد بالنسبة لخصورنا--
but it turns out that this choice overload problem affects us
لكن اتضح ان مشكلة الحمل الزائد للخيار يؤثر علينا
even in very consequential decisions.
حتى في القرارت المنطقية جدا
We choose not to choose,
نختار ان لا نختار
even when it goes against our best self-interests.
حتى ولو كان ذلك ضد مصالحنا الخاصة
So now for the topic of today: financial savings.
الان لعنوان اليوم : المدخرات المالية.
Now I'm going to describe to you a study I did
سوف اشرح لكم اليوم الدراسة التي قمت بها
with Gur Huberman, Emir Kamenica, Wei Jang
مع جور هوبيمان,ايمر كامينيكا, وي جانج
where we looked at the retirement savings decisions
عندما نظرنا في قرارت ادخارات التقاعد
of nearly a million Americans
الخاصة بحوالي مليون من الامريكيين
from about 650 plans
من حوالي 650 باقة
all in the U.S.
على مستوى الولايات المتحدة
And what we looked at
وما راقبناه هو
was whether the number of fund offerings
ما اذا كان عدد عروض الصناديق
available in a retirement savings plan,
متوفرة في باقة ادخارات التقاعد
the 401(k) plan,
باقة التقاعد بخطة 401 (كي),
does that affect people's likelihood
احتمال ان تؤثر على الناس
to save more for tomorrow.
ليدخروا الكثير للغد
And what we found
وما توصلنا اليه
was that indeed there was a correlation.
انه هناك ترابط في الواقع
So in these plans, we had about 657 plans
ففي تلك الباقات ,لدينا حوالي 657 باقة
that ranged from offering people
والتي تراوحت من العرض على الناس
anywhere from two to 59 different fund offerings.
في اي مكان من اثنين الى 59 عرض مختلف للتمويل
And what we found was that,
وما وجدناه كان
the more funds offered,
كلما زاد عدد الصناديق المعروضة
indeed, there was less participation rate.
في الواقع كان هناك اقل نسبة للمشاركة
So if you look at the extremes,
وعلى النقيض اذا نظرت
those plans that offered you two funds,
تلك الباقات التي تعرض عليك صندوقين,
participation rates were around in the mid-70s --
كانت نسبة المشاركة حوالي منتصف السبعينات
still not as high as we want it to be.
مازالت ليست النسبة المطلوبة
In those plans that offered nearly 60 funds,
في تلك الباقات التي تعرض حوالي ال 60 صندوق,
participation rates have now dropped
معدل المشاركة انخفض الان
to about the 60th percentile.
الى حوال 60 في المئة
Now it turns out
الان يتضح
that even if you do choose to participate
انه حتى وان قررت ان تشارك
when there are more choices present,
اذا وجد الكثير من المشاركات,
even then, it has negative consequences.
حتى في تلك الحالة تكون العواقب سلبية
So for those people who did choose to participate,
فلأولئك الاشخاص الذين اختاروا المشاركة
the more choices available,
كلما زاد عدد الخيارات المتاحة
the more likely people were
كلما زاد قابلية الاشخاص
to completely avoid stocks or equity funds.
ليتحاشوا تماما صناديق الاسهم والسندات.
The more choices available,
كلما زادت الخيارات المتاحة,
the more likely they were
كلما كان احتمال
to put all their money in pure money market accounts.
ان يضعوا اموالهم في حسابات اسواق مالية محضة
Now neither of these extreme decisions
الان ليس كلا من هذه القرارات
are the kinds of decisions
هي القرارات
that any of us would recommend for people
التي نرغب في توصية الناس بها
when you're considering their future financial well-being.
عندما تنظر الى وضع مستقبلهم المالي
Well, over the past decade,
في العقد الماضي
we have observed three main negative consequences
راقبنا ثلاث عواقب سلبية
to offering people more and more choices.
لعرض الكثير والكثير من الخيارات على الناس
They're more likely to delay choosing --
هم اكثر قابلية لتأخير اختيارهم--
procrastinate even when it goes against their best self-interest.
والمماطلة حتى ولو كان ذلك ضد مصالحهم الشخصية
They're more likely to make worse choices --
هم اكثر قابلية لاتخاذ الخيارات الاسوأ--
worse financial choices, medical choices.
اسوأ خيارات مالية، اسوأ خيارات طبية
They're more likely to choose things that make them less satisfied,
هم اكثر قابلية لاختيار اشياء تجعلهم اقل رضاءا
even when they do objectively better.
حتى عندما يكونوا موضوعين اكثر
The main reason for this
السبب الرئيسي لهذا
is because, we might enjoy gazing at those giant walls
اننا نستمتع بالتحديق الى تلك الجدران العالية
of mayonnaises, mustards, vinegars, jams,
من المايونيز ,و الماسترد , والخل , و المربى
but we can't actually do the math of comparing and contrasting
لكننا في الواقع لا نستطيع عمل الحسابات اللازمة للمقارنة والمناقضة
and actually picking from that stunning display.
والإنتقاء من ذلك العرض المذهل
So what I want to propose to you today
الذي اريد إقتراحه اليوم
are four simple techniques --
هو اربع تقنيات بسيطة
techniques that we have tested in one way or another
تقنيات جربناها بطريقة او اخرى
in different research venues --
في ميادين بحثية متنوعة--
that you can easily apply
والتي يمكن تطبيقها بسهولة
in your businesses.
في اعمالكم.
The first: Cut.
الاول هو الانقاص
You've heard it said before,
لقد سمعتها من قبل
but it's never been more true than today,
لكن لم تكن حقيقية كما هي اليوم
that less is more.
حيث ان القليل يعني الكثير
People are always upset when I say, "Cut."
الناس يشعرون بخيبة الامل عندما اقول "خفض"
They're always worried they're going to lose shelf space.
انهم دائما قلقون من خسارة مساحة الارفف
But in fact, what we're seeing more and more
لكن في الواقع ,ما يشاهدونه كثيرا وكثيرا
is that if you are willing to cut,
هو انه اذا كنت مستعدا للتخفيض
get rid of those extraneous redundant options,
والقضاء على تلك الخيارات الدخيلة
well there's an increase in sales,
يكون هناك زيادة في المبيعات
there's a lowering of costs,
وخفض في التكاليف
there is an improvement of the choosing experience.
هناك تقدم في خبرة الاختيار
When Proctor &amp; Gamble
عندما أنتقلت "بروكتور اند قامبل"
went from 26 different kinds of Head &amp; Shoulders to 15,
من 25 صنفا من شامبو "هيد اند شولدرز" الى 15,
they saw an increase in sales by 10 percent.
لاحظوا زيادة في المبيعات بنسبة 10 في المائة
When the Golden Cat Corporation
شركة القطة الذهبية
got rid of their 10 worst-selling cat litter products,
تخلصوا من اسوأ عشر منتجات خاصة بنفايات القطط,
they saw an increase in profits
لاحظوا زيادة في المبيعات
by 87 percent --
بحوالي 87 في المائة
a function of both increase in sales
العملية كانت عبارة عن زيادة في المبيعات
and lowering of costs.
وتخفيض في التكاليف
You know, the average grocery store today
تعلم ان متجر البقالة في المتوسط
offers you 45,000 products.
يعرض لكم 45،000 منتجا
The typical Walmart today offers you 100,000 products.
"وول مارت" يعرض اليوم 100،000 منتجا
But the ninth largest retailer,
لكن تاسع اكبر بائع تجزئة
the ninth biggest retailer in the world today
تاسع اكبر معرض تجزئة في العالم اليوم
is Aldi,
هو "الدي" ,
and it offers you only 1,400 products --
وهو يعرض فقط 1،400 منتجا
one kind of canned tomato sauce.
نوع واحد من معجون الطماطم المعلبة
Now in the financial savings world,
الآن، في عالم الادخار المالي,
I think one of the best examples that has recently come out
اعتقد ان احد اكبر الامثلة التي ظهرت مؤخرا
on how to best manage the choice offerings
على كيفية ادارة عروض الخيارات
has actually been something that David Laibson was heavily involved in designing,
كان الشيئ الذي شارك في تصميمه وبكثافة "ديفيد ليبسون"
which was the program that they have at Harvard.
والذي كان برنامج لديهم في هارفارد
Every single Harvard employee
كل موظف في هارفارد
is now automatically enrolled
تلقائيا ملتحق
in a lifecycle fund.
في تمويل مدى الحياة
For those people who actually want to choose,
لاؤلئك الناس الراغبين في الاختيار,
they're given 20 funds,
يعطون 20 صندوقا
not 300 or more funds.
وليس 300 صندوقا
You know, often, people say,
كما تعلمون,يقول الناس دائما,
"I don't know how to cut.
"لا اعلم كيف اخفض
They're all important choices."
انها جميعها خيارات مهمة."
And the first thing I do is I ask the employees,
واول شيئ افعله ان اسأل الموظفين,
"Tell me how these choices are different from one another.
"اخبرني كيف تختلف تلك الخيارات عن بعضها البعض
And if your employees can't tell them apart,
واذا كان موظفوكم غير قادرين على تفصيلها,
neither can your consumers."
لن يتمكن المستهلكين ايضا "
Now before we started our session this afternoon,
قبل ان نبدا فقرتنا هذه الظهيرة
I had a chat with Gary.
كنت اتحدث مع "غاري"
And Gary said that he would be willing
و"غاري" قال انه مستعد
to offer people in this audience
لتقديم عطلة مدفوعة التكاليف
an all-expenses-paid free vacation
للناس في هذا المحفل
to the most beautiful road in the world.
لأجمل شارع في العالم.
Here's a description of the road.
هذا هو وصف الطريق
And I'd like you to read it.
واريد ان اقرأه
And now I'll give you a few seconds to read it
وسوف امنحكم بضع ثواني لتقرأوها
and then I want you to clap your hands
وبعد ذلك اريدكم ان تصفقوا
if you're ready to take Gary up on his offer.
لمجاراة "غاري" في عرضه
(Light clapping)
(تصفيق خفيف)
Okay. Anybody who's ready to take him up on his offer.
حسنا,هل هناك اي شخص جاهز لمجاراة عرضه
Is that all?
هذا كل شيئ؟
All right, let me show you some more about this.
حسنا ,دعوني اعرض عليكم شيء اكثر عن هذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You guys knew there was a trick, didn't you.
انتم تعرفون ان هناك خدعة,اليس كذلك
(Honk)
(ضوضاء)
Now who's ready to go on this trip.
الان من هو الجاهز للقيام بهذه الرحلة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I think I might have actually heard more hands.
اظن انني سمعت الكثير من التصفيق
All right.
حسنا
Now in fact,
في الواقع
you had objectively more information
حصلتم على معلومات اكثر بموضوعية
the first time around than the second time around,
في الجولة الاولى اكثر من الجولة الثانية
but I would venture to guess
ولكن لي الحق ان اخمن
that you felt that it was more real the second time around.
انكم شعرتم ان ذلك اكثر واقعية في المرة الثانية
Because the pictures made it feel
لأن الصور جعلته يبدو
more real to you.
اكثر واقعية لكم
Which brings me to the second technique
وهو ما اخذني للتقنية الثانية
for handling the choice overload problem,
لمعالجة مشكلة زيادة حمل الاختيار
which is concretization.
وهو التجسيد
That in order for people to understand
انه ليكون الناس قادرين على فهم
the differences between the choices,
الفرق بين الاختيارات
they have to be able to understand
يجب ان يكون قادرين على فهم
the consequences associated with each choice,
التبعات المرتبطة بكل اختيار
and that the consequences need to be felt
وتلك التبعات يجب ان تكون ملموسة
in a vivid sort of way, in a very concrete way.
بصورة مجسدة,وصورة واضحة جدا
Why do people spend an average of 15 to 30 percent more
لماذا يقضي الناس متوسط 15 ال 30 في المائة اكثر
when they use an ATM card or a credit card
عندما يستخدمون بطاقة الصراف الالي وبطاقتهم الائتمانية
as opposed to cash?
على العكس من النقد؟
Because it doesn't feel like real money.
لأنها لا تبدو كنقود حقيقية
And it turns out
واتضح
that making it feel more concrete
أن جعله اكثر تجسيديةً
can actually be a very positive tool
يمكن ان يكون اداة ايجابية
to use in getting people to save more.
لجعل الناس يوفرون اكثر
So a study that I did with Shlomo Benartzi
الدراسة التي قمت بها مع شلومو بيناتزي
and Alessandro Previtero,
و اليساندرو بريفيترو,
we did a study with people at ING --
عملنا دراسة مع اشخاص في "اي ان جي" --
employees that are all working at ING --
موظفين جميعهم يعملون في "اي ان جي"--
and now these people were all in a session
وهؤلاء الاشخاص جميعهم في جلسة
where they're doing enrollment for their 401(k) plan.
حيث يقومون بعمل التسجيل للتقاعد بخطة 401 (كي)
And during that session,
وخلال الجلسة
we kept the session exactly the way it used to be,
جهزنا الجلسة على الكيفية التي يجب ان تكون عليها
but we added one little thing.
لكن اضفنا شيئا بسيطا
The one little thing we added
الشيء البسيط الذي اضفناه
was we asked people
كان اننا سألناهم
to just think about all the positive things that would happen in your life
ان يفكروا في الاشياء الايجابية التي سوف تحصل لحياتكم
if you saved more.
اذا ادخرتم اكثر
By doing that simple thing,
بعمل ذلك الشيء البسيط
there was an increase in enrollment by 20 percent
كان هناك زيادة في التسجيل بنسبة 20 في المائة
and there was an increase in the amount of people willing to save
وكان هناك زيادة في عدد الناس الراغبين في الادخار
or the amount that they were willing to put down into their savings account
او المبالغ الراغبين في وضعها في حسابات التوفير الخاصة بهم
by four percent.
بنسبة 4 في المائة
The third technique: Categorization.
التقنية الثالثة : التصنيف
We can handle more categories
يمكننا التعامل مع الكثير من التصنيفات
than we can handle choices.
اكثر من قدرتنا على التعامل مع الخيارات
So for example,
فعلى سبيل المثال
here's a study we did in a magazine aisle.
هذه دراسة عملناها في قسم المجلات
It turns out that in Wegmans grocery stores
اتضح انه في محلات ويجمانز للبقالة
up and down the northeast corridor,
اعلى واسفل الممرات الشمالية الشرقية
the magazine aisles range anywhere
تقبع المجلات في كل مكان
from 331 different kinds of magazines
ابتداء من 331 نوع مختلف من المجلات
all the way up to 664.
انتهاء ب 664 منها
But you know what?
لكن تعلمون ماذا؟
If I show you 600 magazines
اذا عرضت 600 مجلة
and I divide them up into 10 categories,
وثم قسمتها الى عشرة اصناف
versus I show you 400 magazines
مقابل اذا عرضت عليك 400 مجلة
and divide them up into 20 categories,
وقسمتها الى 20 صنف
you believe that I have given you
تعتقدون انني اعطيتكم
more choice and a better choosing experience
الكثير من الخيارات وتجربة اختيار افضل
if I gave you the 400
اذا اعطيتكم 400
than if I gave you the 600.
اكثر منها اذا اعطيتك 600
Because the categories tell me how to tell them apart.
لان التصنيف يخبرني كيف افصلهم
Here are two different jewelry displays.
هنا عرضين مختلفين للمجوهرات
One is called "Jazz" and the other one is called "Swing."
احدهم يسمى "جاز" والاخر اسمه " سوينج"
If you think the display on the left is Swing
اذا اعتقدت ان العرض الى الشمال هو سوينج
and the display on the right is Jazz,
والذي الى اليمين هو جاز
clap your hands.
صفقو بايديكم.
(Light Clapping)
(تصفيق ضعيف)
Okay, there's some.
حسنا,هناك بعض.
If you think the one on the left is Jazz and the one on the right is Swing,
اذا اعتقدت ان الذي الى اليسار هو جاز والذي الى اليمين هو سوينج,
clap your hands.
صفقو بايديكم
Okay, a bit more.
حسنا ,اكثر قليلا.
Now it turns out you're right.
الا اتضح انكم على صواب
The one on the left is Jazz and the one on the right is Swing,
الذي الى اليسار هو جاز والذي الى اليمين هو سوينج,
but you know what?
لكن تعلمون ماذا؟
This is a highly useless categorization scheme.
هذا نموذج للتصنيف عديم النفع بشكل عالي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The categories need to say something
التصنيف يجب ان يقول شيئا
to the chooser, not the choice-maker.
للذي يقوم بالاختيار, وليس لواضع الاختيار
And you often see that problem
وغالبا ما ترى المشكلة
when it comes down to those long lists of all these funds.
عندما ياتي الامر الى تلك القوائم الطويلة المتعلقة بتلك الصناديق الاستثمارية
Who are they actually supposed to be informing?
من هو المعني بالمعلومة؟
My fourth technique: Condition for complexity.
التقنية الرابعة: شرط للتعقيد.
It turns out we can actually
اتضح انه في الواقع
handle a lot more information than we think we can,
يمكننا التعامل مع قدر من المعلومات اكثر من ما نظن
we've just got to take it a little easier.
فقط يجب ان ناخذ الموضوع ببساطة اكثر
We have to gradually increase the complexity.
يجب ان نزيد التعقيد تدريجيا
I'm going to show you one example of what I'm talking about.
ساريكم مثال لما اتحدث عنه
Let's take a very, very complicated decision:
لنأخذ قرار معقد جدا جدا:
buying a car.
شراء سيارة.
Here's a German car manufacturer
هذا مصنع سيارات الماني
that gives you the opportunity to completely custom make your car.
يعطيك الفرصة لتخصيص سيارتك
You've got to make 60 different decisions,
يجب عليك اتخاذ 60 قرار
completely make up your car.
تجهز سياراتك بالكامل
Now these decisions vary
الان تلك القرارات
in the number of choices that they offer per decision.
وبعدد الاختيارت التي يتضمنها كل قرار
Car colors, exterior car colors --
الوان السيارة,اللون الخارجي--
I've got 56 choices.
لدي 56 خيار.
Engines, gearshift -- four choices.
المحركات ,مغيرات التروس-- اربعة اختيارات
So now what I'm going to do
الان الذي سوف اقوم بعمله
is I'm going to vary the order in which these decisions appear.
هو اعادة ترتيب ظهور تلك القرارات
So half of the customers
بحيث ان نصف الزبائن
are going to go from high choice, 56 car colors,
سوف ينتقلون من عدد الخيارات الاعلى ,56 لون سيارة,
to low choice, four gearshifts.
الى عدد الخيارات الاقل’ اربعة نواقل تروس
The other half of the customers
النصف الاخر
are going to go from low choice, four gearshifts,
سوف ينتقلون من عدد الخيارات الاقل ، اربعة نواقل تروس
to 56 car colors, high choice.
الى 56 لون سيارة ,عدد اعلى من الخيارات
What am I going to look at?
مالذي سوف اراقبه؟
How engaged you are.
كيف تتصرف.
If you keep hitting the default button per decision,
اذا وصلت ضغط الزر الافتراضي في كل قرار
that means you're getting overwhelmed,
هذا يعني انه تم الاثقال عليك
that means I'm losing you.
وهذا يعني انني اخسرك
What you find
ما سوف تجدونه
is the people who go from high choice to low choice,
ان الاشخاص الذين ينتقلون من الخيارات الاعلى الى الخيارات الاقل
they're hitting that default button over and over and over again.
يضغطون الزر الافتراضي مرارا وتكرارا
We're losing them.
نحن نخسرهم
They go from low choice to high choice,
والذين ينتقلون من الاقل الى الاعلى
they're hanging in there.
يتعلقون بالامر
It's the same information. It's the same number of choices.
انها نفس المعلومات ونفس العدد من الاختيارات
The only thing that I have done
الشيء الوحيد الذي عملته
is I have varied the order
هو تغيير الترتيب
in which that information is presented.
في الطريقة التي تقدم بها المعلومة
If I start you off easy,
اذا بدات بك من الاسهل,
I learn how to choose.
اتعلم كيف اختار
Even though choosing gearshift
بالرغم من ان اختيار ناقل الحركة
doesn't tell me anything about my preferences for interior decor,
لا يخبرني اي شيء عن ديكوري الداخلي
it still prepares me for how to choose.
مازال يجهزني الى كيفية الاختيار
It also gets me excited about this big product that I'm putting together,
انه يحمسني تجاه هذا المنتج الكبير الذي اقوم بتجميعه,
so I'm more willing to be motivated
اذا انا اكثر قابلية لاكون متفاعل
to be engaged.
ولاكون عالق
So let me recap.
دعوني الخص ما سبق
I have talked about four techniques
تحدثت عن تقنيات
for mitigating the problem of choice overload --
لتخفيف مشكلة زيادة حمل الاختيار --
cut -- get rid of the extraneous alternatives;
خفض-- تخلص من البدائل الزائدة
concretize -- make it real;
جسده-- اجعله حقيقة
categorize -- we can handle more categories, less choices;
التصنيف-- يمكننا التعامل مع تصنيفات اكثر وخيارات اقل
condition for complexity.
شروط للتعقيد
All of these techniques that I'm describing to you today
جميع هذه التقنيات التي اشرحها لكم اليوم
are designed to help you manage your choices --
صممت لتساعدكم على ادارة اختياراتكم
better for you, you can use them on yourself,
من الافضل لكم استخدامها بانفسكم
better for the people that you are serving.
وافضل للاشخاص الذين تخدمونهم
Because I believe that the key
لانني اؤمن أن المفتاح
to getting the most from choice
للحصول على الكثير من الاختيار
is to be choosy about choosing.
ان تكون حسن الاختيار تجاه الاختيار
And the more we're able to be choosy about choosing
وكلما كنا اكثر خيارية تجاه الاختيار
the better we will be able
كلما كنا قادرين بشكل افضل
to practice the art of choosing.
على التدرب على فن الاختيار
Thank you very much.
اشكركم جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)